

Auscar Wambiya

Born 14th of April 1984 milestones14@gmail.com +254720920491

CERTIFICATES

Communication

This certificate helps you develop the knowledge and skills to understand how the media works and the role it has in society.

Dec 2009

Certified Associate in Project Management (CAMP)

Nov 2019

Human Resource Management

The HR certificate provides the foundation in human resource principles and practices demanded by employers.

Mar 2020

ASSOCIATIONS

International Association of Community Development Practitioners

Member

Association of Community Development Practitioners - Kenya Member

LANGUAGES

Luo

Spoken: Native • Written: Native

Swahili

Spoken: Fluent • Written: Fluent

English

Spoken: Fluent • Written: Fluent

-

INTRO

I have served Kenya's Public Service and with International Non-Governmental Organizations including Care International in Kenya and ChildFund International for over 20 years. I am wildly enthusiastic about results. I bring dedication, hard work, self-motivation, collaboration, team approaches, confidence, proactivity and integrity to whatever assignment I am entrusted with. I believe in participatory approaches to delivering Strategy for Teams, Training for Emerging Leaders and Development for practitioners. I believe that Together Each Achieves More



WORK EXPERIENCE

0

President

1 ST; MILESTONES CONSULTANTS • Sep 2022 - Present

Responsibilities

- o Production and Development of Strategic Plans for Institutions
- o Support organizations with execution of strategic change and organizational change management
- o Sourcing for consultancies on Strategy, Leadership training and Development research opportunities
- o Facilitation of Teams on Team Building and Interpersonal Group Dynamic Skills
- o Conducting community development training and research activities for local and International Non-Governmental Organizations and Community Based Organizations
- o Recruitment of Research Assistants, Associate Consultants and required staff in the event of training and research opportunities
- o Engaging, negotiating and signing training and other development consultancy works with local and international Non-Governmental Organizations, Community Based Organizations, Faith Based Organizations, and Trusts e.t.c.
- o Conducting motivational talks aimed at Personal Empowerment, Self Actualization and Self Discovery in Seminars, Conventions, Schools among other forums
- o Training and Mentorship of Students Leaders
- o Policy Development and Analysis
- o Organizational Capacity Assessment, Building and Performance Monitoring and Measurement

Q

Ag. Chief of Staff - Office of The Governor County Government of Siaya • Aug 2020 - Aug 2022

Responsibilities

- o Liaise closely with the Governor and the Deputy Governor to ensure the overall smooth running of the Governorship
- o Manage the Governor and The Deputy Governor's diary
- o Provide guidelines on implementing the Governor's agenda
- o Liaise with the Governor's Personal Assistant and Advisors in the implementation of the Governor's mandate
- o Supervise the Governor's Press Unit, Protocol, transport, security and other administrative offices in the Governorship in liaison with other departments
- o Have oversight over the Governor's residence as directed by the Governor
- o Coordinate the Governor's international and regional visits
- o Link the Governorship with the rest of the Government
- o Other roles assigned by The Governor from time to time

Director of Communications County Government of Siaya • Apr 2019 – Aug 2022

Responsibilities

- o Development and dissemination of County Government Communication regulations, policies and procedures
- o Coordinating Communication among various Departments within the government and with external actors including media correspondents, editors and media owners
- o Coordination of Government Communication with stakeholders and Partners
- o Writing Official Speeches for the Governor, the Deputy Governor, County Executive Committee Members and County Government of Siaya Staff
- o Designing and populating the Monthly, Quarterly and Annual County Newsletter
- o Communicating the government position though various media including social (Twitter, Facebook & Instagram), electronic (Radio and Television) and print (Newspapers)
- o Participating in the development of key communication documents including County Integrated Development Plans, Strategic Plans, Annual Development Plans and Annual Program Budgets

Asst. Director of Communications County Government of Siaya • Nov 2017 – Apr 2019

Responsibilities

- o Assisting the Director of Communications in the Development and dissemination of County Government Communication Policy and Procedures
- o Working with the Director of Communications in coordinating Communication among various Departments within the government and with external actors including media correspondents, editors and owners
- o Coordination of Government Communication with stakeholders and Partners in support of The Communication Director
- o Working with the Director of Communication to write Official Speeches for the Governor, the Deputy Governor, County Executive Committee Members and County Government of Siaya Key Staff and other

Programs Manager

The Parliamentary Service Commission • Jul 2013 - Aug 2017

Responsibilities

- o Organizing community training workshops on Alego Usonga Constituency plans o Public Civic Education Engagements and working with local Community Organizations
- o Development of constituency proposals to seek external funding
- o Advising the Member of National Assembly, Alego Usonga Constituency, 11th Parliament on Development Affairs.
- o Representing the Member of National Assembly, Alego Usonga, 11th Parliament in the National Government Constituency Development Fund Committee
- o Public Relations and Management of Expectations
- o Writing speeches, newspaper articles and memos on behalf of and for the Member of National Assembly
- o Addressing press conferences, participating in electronic and social media forums to articulate the vision of the Member of National Assembly in the best interest of the constituency

o Perform any other duty assigned by the Member of National Assembly

Program Officer

ChildFund International • Feb 2012 - Jun 2013

Responsibilities

- o Working closely with the Local partner structures to facilitate the design, planning, implementation and monitoring of child centered Deprived Excluded and Vulnerable Children programs in the assigned project site.
- o Enhance Child and Youth Participation in Programs
- o Ensure quality and timely implementation as well as monitoring of projects in line with Area Operation Plans and Budgets, ChildFund Policy and Deprived Excluded and Vulnerable Children framework.
- o Enhance the organizational and institutional development of project site communities to move towards development and federation.
- o Facilitate the creation and/or strengthening of quality relationships between the Community Organization project and the available NGO and GoK partners at the Community, Divisional and District Levels.
- o Ensure regular reporting and documentation of project progress.
- o Facilitate community mobilization and action for development.
- o Guides community organizations in developing workable proposals and budgets.
- o Facilitate community training and capacity building initiatives
- o Work with other Community Based Organizations (CBO) staff to implement ChildFund Kenya core strategic areas in Healthy and Secure Infants, Educated and confident children and Skilled and involved youth.
- o Work closely with the CBO Sponsor Relations Officer and ChildFund's Sponsor Relations Coordinator to support sponsor relations activities in line with ChildFund Kenya policy on sponsorship and cluster/national guidelines and agreements.

Field Officer - Siaya Care International • May 2008 – Dec 2011

Responsibilities

- o Reporting to the Program Manager, develop field level project activities implementation work plans, budgets and reports in harmony with a Health Outcomes Program for Voluntary Savings & Loans (VS&L) and effective Selection Planning and Management (SPM) of Income Generating Activities
- o Facilitate skills building among beneficiary HIV/AIDS support groups, women, men and the general community members to recognize potential for individual empowerment and incorporate ways of attitude change towards better times.
- o Facilitate capacity building on business skills Selection, Planning and Management (SPM) of Income Generating Activities and Voluntary Savings and Loans (VSL) training for identified members of Community Based Organizations and Groups taking care of orphans and vulnerable children due to HIV/AIDS.
- o Technically supporting Community Based Trainers nominated through Community Based Organizations, partner civil society organizations carrying out direct implementation of Voluntary Savings and Loans and Selection Planning and Management of Income Generating activities, follow up and support supervision of implementing beneficiary nanny groups and Orphans and Vulnerable Children.
- o Provide back stopping role for Siaya Health Outcomes Programme on VS&L and report to the VS&L Country office on VS&L data using the Management Information

Project Officer

Center for Education Population Environment and Development (C.E.P.E.D) • Apr 2007 - Apr 2008

Responsibilities:

- o Community Mobilization and coordinating child rights advocacy activities
- o Community education on HIV/AIDS & related issues
- o Organizing Workshops, Seminars, Stakeholders meetings and hosting some of such meetings at the office level.
- o Rehabilitating orphans and vulnerable children from forced child labor and integrating them back to school while attaching those of age to apprenticeship training in carpentry, tailoring, dressmaking, mechanics, plumbing, welding among other vocational training courses
- o Collecting Data (orphans' inventory), Baseline surveys and report writing.
- o Facilitating Guidance and Counseling courses to orphans and vulnerable children from the fishing industry of Lake Kanyaboli.

Project Site Coordinator CARE Kenya • Mar 2005 – Mar 2007

Responsibilities:

- o Community mobilization and sensitization on economic empowerment
- o Facilitating the creation of community groups to participate in savings and loaning activities and subsequent training on effective business Selection, Planning and Management
- o Training community groups and subsequent formation of Voluntary Savings and Loans Associations.
- o Constantly monitoring and reporting on progress of implementation of the methodology.

Field Assistant

Center for Education, Population, Environment and Development • Mar 2004 – Feb 2005

Responsibilities: -

- o Field data collection and analysis
- o Community mobilization for social change
- o Training on child rights at school community level
- o Monitoring child sponsorship programmes on vocational training.



EDUCATION

Master of Arts - Development

Catholic University of Eastern; Africa, Eldoret • Jan 2019 – Oct 2021

Master of Arts in Development Studies

Bachelor of Arts - Social

Catholic University of East • Sep 2013 - Oct 2018

Bachelor of Arts in Social Sciences (Political Science)

Higher Diploma

PREMESE Africa Development • Jan 2008 – Jun 2013

Higher Diploma in Community Development and Project Management

Diploma

PREMESE Africa Development • Jan 2006 – Sep 2008

Diploma in Community Development

Certificate in Automobile Engineering Athi-River Vocational Training • Jan 2004 – Jun 2004

Certificate in Automobile Engineering

K.C.S.E

Mwer High School • Jan 1999 - Nov 2002

High School Certificate

•

SKILLS

Logistics planning and management Budgeting, financial planning Project implementation

Reporting Project management Team leadership Training delivery Planning

Problem solving Listening Leadership skills Office tools: Word, Excel, Outlook

Networking Dealing with difficult people Decision making

Interpersonal relationships building Conflict and crisis management Communication

Capacity planning Ability to coordinate



HOBBIES



Giving

Running

Reading



LINKS



https://www.linkedin.com/in/auscar-wambiya/details/experience/



REFERENCES



Cornel Rasanga • Governor - County Government of Siaya (2013 - 2022)

Manager • +254 0722707926 • rasangaamoth@gmail.com

P

Prof. Paul Akelo Ogula • Professor - Catholic University of Eastern Africa

Teacher • +254 0722481142 • ogulapaul@gmail.com



Dorothy Owino • County Executive Committee Member - County Government of Siaya (2022)

Manager • +254 0721986272 • dowinoakinyi@gmail.com